Hello everyone, welcome back to Visitors Life Channel.  So in the
Hello大家好呀，歡迎回到來者生活頻道。 那麼
last video, we are talking about coming, this public
話說上一個影片呀，咱們就說著來緊啦，這公
's charges will increase significantly.  So there are three people who can
的收費吧將會大幅提升的。 那有三個人吧可
enjoy this free service of public health care with this ID card
以憑著這個身份證，享有這個公營醫療免費的
.  So yeah, the difference is this aid person.  75 years old said that the
服務架。 那麼呀，分別是這個援人士吧。 75歲說
above people who are receiving the elderly living allowance, and the current remote society
以上拿緊長者生活津貼的人士，和現在遠社
is belonging to another
是 屬於別
, so in fact, they are in an economic dilemma, what is the way to
，那其實自己也處於了個經濟困難啦，有啥辦
get this public fee reduction?  So this time the video we
法可以獲得公的費用減免呢？ 所以這次影片我
will tell you in detail that this authority actually has a medical expenses
們會跟大家詳細說一下這管局其實有個醫療費用
used minus to be returned to the citizens to apply.  So this time in the video
的減去被回各位市民去申請的。 那麼這次影片吧
we will introduce this medical fee reduction mechanism of application qualifications
我們將介紹一下這個醫療費用減免機制的申請資
how to do the application and some application common questions
格怎麼去做申請和一些申請常見的問題呢
?  It's not too late Now we get started right away.
? 事不宜遲 現在我們立即開始。
In fact, this medical expense reduction has been available before, it
其實這個醫療費用減了，之前已經有的了，他
is based on the patient and his and his family's Japanese and assets to
是根據病人和他同著家人的日式和資產去
determine the reduction in supply of medical expenses.  Successful patients are going to
定供應醫療費用的減馬額。 成功的病人是會獲
receive one more medical bill with face proof of loss.  Basically eligible can
得多一張醫療費用面證明輸。 基本上合資格可
apply for a full discount
以申請個全減
.  So the latest supply of medical expenses use reduction system This medical expenses and
。 那麼最新的供醫療費用減制下吧 這個醫療費和
the category is very broad applicable to medical projects including there urgent things etc  The purpose is to increase the price, so this side does the price, then that side has
幅將這個公項目加價架 那這邊做價，那那邊就
to do some rest.  So this medical project reduced
要做過一些休化吧。 那這個醫療項目減吧
, will do some advantageous measures so such as relaxing this applicant into it
，將會做些優的措施那麼例如放寬這個申請人入
, and the definition of asset family received and the site of this
呀，和資產家庭的定義收了和現場這個有
validity period and so on.
效期等等嘎。
So this supply of medical expenses with the reduction it is through the median of everyone's family
那這個供應醫療費用減免它是透過大家的家庭
entry, and assets to judge the amount of the reduction everyone gets
入式中位數了，和資產去判斷大家獲得減金
.  First we introduce this type of medical expenses with reduced
額。 首先了我們也介紹一下這樣的型醫療費用減的
applications the latest interest and assets for a family.  So
申請吧 最新的息和資產以一人家庭為呀。 那麼
from the previous total monthly income of 5,300 dollars adjusted to $ 7,575
從以前的每月總收入5300元吧 調升到去$7575
dollars, which means that as long as your income does not exceed $ 7,575 per type, you
元也就是說只要你每種收入不超過7575元吧，你
contribute to medical expenses.  So as for this half
供醫療費用吧全面架了。 那至於這個半
monthly total income it does not exceed the
每月的總收入吧就不過
dollar to be eligible.  Of course, as mentioned earlier, in addition to looking at your
蚊啦就合資格了。 當然頭先都講到除了看你
monthly income, you also need to see your assets in
每月入息之外，還需要看看你的資產
this table about assets
這個關於資產的表格，以頭先個人為例你的資
?  So
以41500元吧，大幅調高到去26000元㗎？ 那麼
if with the elderly and is even better, really plus there is a way to have a
如果跟老人家同就更好吧，真的是加有一路有
because if the house has an elderly family over 65 years old
一部因為如果家裡有一位65歲以上的老人家吧
, your assets line will be another 80 plus 06 dollars.
，你的資產行額是會另外再加多168000元㗎。
So the calculation of the asset, at most will count two elderly people plus.
那麼個資產的計算吧，最多是會計兩位老人加。
What about the right hand side of the grid?  As you can see, if you have
那麼格的右手邊呢？ 大家可以看到，如果家裡有
one or two elderly people in your family, you apply for this
一位或兩位老人家的時候，你申請這個供應
asset grid that provides medical expenses with reductions
醫療費用減免的資產格
.  The second thing is that receiving changed the definition of family, so
。 第二樣東西啦，就是收改了家庭的定義，那即
what does it mean?  In fact, it is divided into this patient and this non-
是如何呢？ 其實就是分這個受病人和這個非受
patient.  They have to calculate the entries and asset ranges are different
病人㗎。 他們要計算的入式和資產範圍都不同
.  So first, the recipients are those who are not divided or under the age of 18
架。 那麼首先吧，受病人是指未分或未滿18歲
, or who are still receiving full-day education between the ages of 18 and 25
，又或者18至25歲仍受全日教育的人士
.  This person's entry and assets are needed to count the
。 這個人士吧 他入式和資產是需要計入他和的
entry and assets of his parents and his parents, the originator and his brothers and sisters.
父母呀、發人和的兄弟姊妹的入式和資產
As for this ticket
至於這個飛
patient, there are two situations
病人吧，有兩種情況啊，如果這個
.  However, it will not count his parents, family members,
撐架。 不過就不會算他的父母、發家會人，又
or brothers and sisters' assets and frame, even if they live together do not need
或者兄弟姊妹的資產同架，即使一起住也不需要
to continue
要繼
if not married if not married to
如果沒結婚的話啦，他就當一個一天人家庭去
apply for a family  This supply fee use reduction is not necessary to continue the
申請他申請這個供應費用減免這是不需要繼
whole application process this has simplified submitted a lot of entry and
整個申請的流程這都簡化了交了很多的入式和
asset proof documents frame is an example now you are 30 years old already out of the social
資產證明文件架 舉個例子 現在你30歲已經出來社
house things  With wearing however unlucky,
會做著事情但是跟家裡同穿的不過不幸啦，因
because there are some long-term
為有些長期
hospital visits, to your economy on it, have caused a certain
醫院做複診，對你的經濟上吧，也造成一定壓
pressure and.  So if you apply for this supply fee use of the reduction is only to
力同 。 這樣如果你申請這個供應費用的減只是
submit and asset information can be framed even if you have and wear
交入和資產資料就可以了 即使你有同穿的
brothers, sisters and parents to do it, do not need to submit the medical and property information
兄弟姊妹和父母吧，也不需要交入吧和資產
.  The second scenario is that you are married and
去給醫做查的。 第二個情況就是你結婚了和你
match you, with your parents living together.  So your parents retired, the Lord has to
配，父母一起住。 那你父母退休吧，就主要
rely on their amount of annuities, pensions these Japanese style this to live
靠他們額的年金呀，退休金這些日式呢去過退
retirement life.  So because of this you have to see a more serious disease
休生活的。 那因為這你要看一個比較嚴重的病
, have spent a lot of money in the take advantage and contract fees there.  So what if you
，也花了不少錢了在趁金和約費那裡了。 那麼
want to apply for this supply fee use reduction?  Then you will need to
如果了想申請這個供應費用減呢？ 那你就是需
hand over you and your spouse's Japanese style and the asset certificate is ready
要交你和你配偶的日式啦和資產證就可以了
.  Then the parents you are with, there is no need to calculate, which
了。 那你同的父母啦，就不需要計算的，也就是
means that their annuities, pensions, these Japanese-style certificates do not have to
說他們的年金呀退休金這些日式證明咧是不用
pay.
交 。
The third item is to use this medical expenses for the validity period of the face
第三項化了 就是將這個醫療費用面的有效期吧
, the site to 18 months.  So in the past, this medical expenses with a
這，現場到18個月了。 那以往吧 這個醫療費用
face certificate, after being approved, there is only 12 months of the term
面證明書吧，獲批之後吧 有期就得12個月的唧
.  After that, you have to apply again, and you have to submit some
。 完了之後又要再做申請了，又要交過一些入
entry-level asset documents to do it.  However, this coming reduction has a period that will be
式資產文件去做架。 不過來緊這個減啦 有期會
from now 12 months, the scene poured to 18 months.  So
從現在12個月了，現場倒去18個月了。 那麼在
within these 18 months, the patient can apply for
這18個月內吧，病人吧可以在這段時間再申請
this medical fee waiver again during this period.  If the patient's Japanese style and
這個醫療費用免的期。 如果病人的日式啊同資
assets have not changed, there is no need to submit documents for an economic
產都沒有改變的，就不用再交文件做經濟審搜審
review.  So later expected in the middle of the year, we can directly in
查了。 那遲點預計在年中吧，大家直情可以在
this HA high this APP, teach application and do during.  So
這個HA高這個APP吧，教申請和做期間。 那麼
yeah back to the patients leave.
呀返各位病人假。
Then the application method is actually very simple.  The first step I
那申請方法吧，其實很簡單的唧。 第一步我建
suggest you go to the HSE medical expense reduction economic review calculation
議大家去翻醫管局醫療費用減免經濟審查計算
formula.  2016 this latest version, so you can scan
式 。 2016年這個最新版本，那麼大家可以掃描右
this c on the right, or you can click the link under the video
手邊這個c吧，又或者可以在影片下面按回個
.  Then according to the situation described in the video earlier enter the
連結 . 然後根據回頭才影片所說的情況進入你
number of patients in your home.  65 years old is indeed the number of elderly people over and above
家裡的病人數吧。 65歲實以上同的長者人數了
.  and monthly household income and total assets for the entire family.
。 和整個家庭的每月家庭收入和總資產。
So he will help you about until you are eligible to apply.
那他呢就會幫大家大約到你合資格申請啦。
However, this program is just a reference.  To be approved for this
不過這個程式啦，只是個參考的而已。 批到這個
face, we have to look at the actual trial situation of the HKMA.  So
面這就要看看醫管局的實際審情況了。 那麼查了
after checking the qualifications.  Then you can prepare your ID
合資格之後吧. 那麼你可以準備你的身份證明文
documents.  Documents proving family income for the last 6 months and
件 . 最近6個月，家庭收入的證明文件件和
this asset document.  So regarding this income proof document,
這個資產文件架。 那麼關於這個收入證明文件，
it includes the bank statement for the last 6 months, the
就包括有最近6個月的銀行月結單、量單部
statement of the annuity issued by the Ministry of Quantity and so on.  So as to in this asset audit
廈發年金的結單等等嘎。 那至於在這個資產審
, it includes all of your individuals for at least the last six months
方面吧，就包括你最少過去六個月的所有個人
, and joint bank accounts so will be betting accounts, so if
吧，和聯名的銀行戶口這樣會的投注戶口這樣如
you have an annuity or plan or plan insurance  The
如果你有年金或保險計劃吧，那他年金計劃或
cash value of the insurance plan is calculated.  There are also
者保險計畫的現金價值這也是計算㗎。 還有股
stocks, funds, bonds of the value of it, are calculated this asset
票呀基金呀債券的價值啦，也是計算這個資產
part of the frame In addition, it is the property, land, parking spaces, etc.
部分架另外啦，就是物業呀、土地呀、車位等
are needed to be calculated in the
等也是需要計算在資產
relevant assets  The social services department of the hospital, the
和有關的文件到這個公納醫院的社會服務部，
comprehensive family service center of the society, carry out the guess.  The social worker
社的綜合家庭服務中心吧，進行猜架。 那麼社工
will then judge the applicant's family situation based on the documents submitted by the applicant
就會根據申請人交出來文件去判斷他的家庭狀
, thereby conducting a trial search review.  If you are eligible
況，從而進行審搜審查的。 那合乎資格的話咧
, you will be issued a face certificate for medical expenses.  And the
，就會發這個醫療費用面證明書架啦。 而證明
certificate, will also the patient after being approved, need a negative golden
書嘞，也都會病人獲批後吧，需要負的金
stomach, and this expiration date grid.  If unlucky, the
胃吧，和這個到期日格。 假如不好彩啦，申
application does not get
請不獲得
fog writing social work he will tell the patient to apply back
霧寫社工 他也會跟病人說回申請
.
嘎。
So with some friends, you might ask.  Now he has
那有些朋友吧，就可能會問了。 現在啦 他也有
a facebook for medical expenses, but I heard that there are
張醫療費用的面書，但聽到了，2026年之後有
some adjustments after 2026, so he will not be able to do this now?  So here you can
D調整，那他現在將這會不會的呢？ 那麼這裡就
rest assured that you will not.  The existing medical expense exemption books are still
放心你是不會的。 現有的醫療費用免書是仍然
valid.  In addition, some friends are asking, the previous
有效㗎。 另外啦，有些朋友也問呀，頭先的申
application, is about the elderly or ordinary families so,
請吧，都是關於一些長者或普通的家庭吧 那，
if the disabled, what to help them apply for medical
如果是傷殘人士，有什麼去幫他們申請一些醫療
treatment?  About this real person so, in fact, they
費用的減呢? 關於這個實人士吧那麼，其實他們
automatically have a medical expenses use of the reduction and face frame here to be
自動也有一個醫療費用的減同面架 這裡就要根
based on that person his disability degree to the reduction is quite a lot.
據翻那人士他的傷殘程度吧去的減是多少的。
So of course, if there is a person who has given birth, he can participate in this
那當然了，如果有產人士了，他可以參加這個
medical expenses using the face selection mechanism to this medical expenses with the face certificate
醫療費用選擇面機制去這個醫療費用面證明書呢
?  So actually it is possible.
? 那其實也是可以的。
Good video to come here first, so the proof as mentioned earlier, what is coming
好影片來到這裡先，那麼證如頭先所說啦，即將來臨
?  This company's various medical expenses spend quite a lot, so we have
這? 這公的各醫療費用吧不少啊，那所以大
more to trust this reduction mechanism.  You can use this
家更要信用這個減免機制吧。 可以用這個經
economic review calculation formula, the first calculation is that you do not meet this application
濟審查計算式咯，第一計自己不符合這個申請
qualification?  If you are eligible, you must apply now in 2026
資格啊？ 如果符合的話，就要在2026年馬上做
.  Especially some long-term need for treatment or follow-up visits,
申請吧。 尤其一些長期需要治療吧或複診，
or old friends, because after all, a few fields count, so a year
或者老友，因為始終吧，少數場計，這樣一年
helps us save a lot of money.  And about some public applications
都幫大家省很多錢啊。 而關於一些公共的申請
, or social welfare matters do not understand, are welcome to
這，或者社福事項有不明白的地方，也歡迎在
leave a comment below with us, so we will try to answer.
下面留言跟我們㗎，那我們也會盡量解答的。
If you find it useful, remember to like this video to share with your
如果你覺得有用的，記得like這個影片分享給你
friends, and subscribe to our channel
身邊的朋友，還有subscribe我們的channel
See you in the next video, bye bye
了 我們下影片再見，拜拜